A Guide to the Papers of the Twin Oaks Community,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Councils
  - K. Planning Council
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1988, 24 items. (Box-folder 26:1)
      Documents pertaining to the 1988 Trade-off Games where all members have an opportunity to prioritize funding and plan the Twin Oaks budget for each year.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 47 items. (Box-folder 26:2)
      Planwriting worksheets for Agriculture to Domestic Councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 64 items. (Box-folder 26:3)
      Planwriting worksheets HEW to Transportation and Maintenance Councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 25 items. (Box-folder 26:4)
      Trade-off games.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 120 items. (Box-folder 26:5)
      Priority requests.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 22 items. (Box-folder 26:6)
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 19 items. (Box-folder 27:1)
      Priorities; planner meeting notes.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1989, 48 items. (Box-folder 27:2)
      Priorities.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1990; 1993-1994, 5 items. (Box-folder 27:3)
      Trade-off Game for 1990; Ongoing 1990; OTRA Index for 1993 Midyear Trade-off Game; 1994 Mid-year Trade-off Game.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1995, 26 items. (Box-folder 27:4)
      Documents pertaining to the Trade-off Game for 1995.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1995, 19 items. (Box-folder 27:5)
      Packets titled The 1995 Ongoing Trade-off Game filled out by Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1996, 42 items. (Box-folder 27:6)
      Packets titled The 1996 Ongoing Trade-off Game filled out by Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1996, 60 items. (Box-folder 27:7)
      Packets titled OTRA Game 1996 filled out by Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1996, 23 items. (Box-folder 27:8)
      Packets titled The 1996 Ongoing Trade-off Game and Playing the Game filled out by Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1997, 32 items. (Box-folder 27:9)
      Packets titled OTRA Game 1997 filled out by Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1975-1976, 1 item. (Box-folder 28:1)
      Notebook containing Money and Labor sections.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1976 April-September, 1 item. (Box-folder 28:2)
      Notebook containing Summary, Labor, and Money sections.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1976 December-1977 December, 1 item. (Box-folder 28:3)
      Notebook containing a Labor section.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1978, 1 item. (Box-folder 28:4)
      Notebook with Farm and Food and Income and Non-Income Council sections.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1979, 1 item. (Box-folder 28:5)
      Notebook labeled Economic Plan Process.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1977-1980, 126 item. (Box-folder 29:1)
      General economic plans; balance sheets; monthly breakdowns by council; priorities and allocations.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1984, 1 item. (Box-folder 29:2)
      Notebook with background data and planwriting questionnaires.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1978-1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 29:3)
      Notebook labeled, Econ Plan- Council Background Data '78, '79, '80, for Outreach, Planning, Support, and Transportation and Maintenance Councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1979-1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 30:1)
      Notebook with priority requests.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1978-1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 30:2)
      Notebook with council background data.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1978-1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 30:3)
      Notebook containing support data.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1980, 1 item. (Folder 31:1)
      Notebook with 1980 planwriting worksheets for non-income areas by council.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 31:2)
      Notebook labeled Farm Decision.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1981, 1 item. (Box-folder 31:3)
      Notebook labeled Econ Plan.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1974-1977, 1 item. (Box-folder 31:4)
      Notebook containing financial and labor reports, community development plans, financial and labor predictions, priorities activity, summaries, three-month reviews, and six-month reviews.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1984, 1 item. (Box-folder 31:5)
      Notebook with the papers, meeting notes, and five-year projections as a part of the 1984 Economic Plan.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1984, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:1)
      Notebook labeled, 1984 Planwriting.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1984, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:2)
      Notebook with money and labor reports.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:3)
      Notebook for the Income Council.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:4)
      Notebook with the papers and meeting notes for the 1985 Economic Plan.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:5)
      First of three notebooks with the budget priorities for various councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:6)
      Second of three notebooks with the budget priorities for various councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 32:7)
      Third of three notebooks with the budget priorities for various councils.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 33:1)
      Notebook with the three-month review for 1985.
    - Planning Council. Economic Planning, 1985, 1 item. (Box-folder 33:2)
      Notebook related for the midyear trade-off game.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Labor Credits, 1967-1988, 57 items. (Box-folder 33:3)
      Notes, instructions, and policies on personal service credits, or PSCs.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Labor Directory, 1985-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 33:4)
      List of workers in various councils.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Labor Exchange, 1976-1988; n.d., 22 items. (Box-folder 33:5)
      Trips to other communities such as Geseundheit, Mettanokit, Dandelion, Springtree, and East Wind; information about the Federation of Egalitarian Communities.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Hiring, 1987, 2 items. (Box-folder 33:6)
      Opinion and idea papers and notes on outside hired labor.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Hole Policy, 1981-1989, 12 items. (Box-folder 33:7)
      Proposals, policies, and notes on labor hole, which concerns meeting labor requirements; planners' meeting notes.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Job Opportunities, 1973-1987, 5 items. (Box-folder 33:8)
      Data and letters about job opportunities.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. K-Shift, 1986-1989, 4 items. (Box-folder 33:9)
      Labor policies and proposals.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Meeting Notes, 1976-1987, 35 items. (Box-folder 33:10)
      Proposed federation policy on labor exchanges; letters from the Federation of Egalitarian Communities.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Opinion Papers, 1975-1988, 19 items. (Box-folder 33:11)
      Opinion and idea papers about labor.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Policy, 1990 June, 1 item. (Box-folder 34:1)
      Twin Oaks labor system principles, policies, and instructions.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Quotas, 1975; 1982-1983; 1987-1989, 19 items. (Box-folder 34:2)
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Sabbatical, 1982; 1984-1989; n.d., 23 items. (Box-folder 34:3)
      Meeting notes on labor sabbatical; surveys; leave of absence option; member opinion, idea paper, and request for various types of leave of absence; discussion notes. OS Leave of absence options included.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Labor sheets, 1983; 1985-1986, 3 items. (Box-folder 34:4)
      Charts and labor data.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Skills Inventory, [1984; n.d.], 2 items. (Box-folder 34:5)
      Inventories for various aspects of Twin Oaks.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Summary and Comparison, 1973-1976, 12 items. (Box-folder 34:6)
      Data and charts with labor statistics. OS Graphs of the data.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Surplus, 1988 January-February, 6 items. (Box-folder 34:7)
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Surveys, 1984, 35 items. (Box-folder 34:8)
      Survey; results.
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Surveys, 1974; n.d., 93 of items. (Box-folder 34:9)
    - Planning Council. Labor Planning. Vacation Balance Statistics, 1983-1988, 12 items. (Box-folder 34:10)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Acquisitions of land, 1968-1975, 27 items. (Box-folder 34:11)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Forms for space use, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 34:12)
      Master copy.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Functional Relationships for use of space, 1975; 1985; n.d., 22 items. (Box-folder 34:13)
      Charts; instruction; surveys/notes.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1974-1976, 7 items. (Box-folder 34:14)
      Juniper Adult/Child Residence; heating comparisons between wood and electric.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1977, 12 items. (Box-folder 34:15)
      Statement of opposition to construction of 640-industrial steel building; meeting notes about 640 building, industry, urban density, and zoning for agriculture, recreation, industry etc.; Merion, Tupelo site, and building plans.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Planning Unit Development and Zoning, 1978-1979; 1982-1984, 14 items. (Box-folder 35:1)
      Twin Oaks Community Planning Unit Development Master Plan Proposal to include Twin Oaks in the Louisa County master plan; correspondence from Louis Massaro about the Twin Oaks planning process report and his visit; report on Yossi Amir's visit and a summary of ideas about a comprehensive planning project.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Proposals, 1978, 39 items. (Box-folder 35:2)
      Proposal for Merion cabin to be used as hammock office; maps of Twin Oaks lay-out; notes on proposal to Louisa County to assist with zoning in Louisa; questionnaire of interests and skills in construction; opinion and idea paper on the Tupelo work space.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Merion, 1977-1988, 18 items. (Box-folder 35:3)
      Report on the financial aspects of selling Merion; news about the sale of Merion and subsequent foreclosure; Hammock Committee proposal to use Merion for hammock office. OS Notes on Merion included.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1977-1979, 14 items. (Box-folder 35:4)
      Meeting notes about canoes, a varnished shed and greenhouse. OS Meeting notes included.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Applications for changes in land/space use, 1979-1989, 85 items. (Box-folder 35:5)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Architectural drawings. Residences, 1979-1980, 1 item. (Box-folder 35:6)
      Architectural drawings of Ta Chai, Morningstar, Harmony, Oneida, Tupelo, Degania, Llano.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1980, 19 items. (Box-folder 35:7)
      Meeting notes about many issues including child cabin use; child education and Grande Shuffle; Kitchen Dining Complex, Tupelo work space and Merion cabins; Compost; music practice room; calf yard; woodshop. OS meeting notes included.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Meeting Notes, 1981; n.d., 18 items. (Box-folder 35:8)
      Meeting notes about many issues including building plans; food storage; Grand Shuffle; Merion cabin; music room; members taking off time; Ridge Road Right of Way; New Farm Road; children's play area; community space; sewer line; varnish shed; future industrial plan; library needs; space for indexing; Oakynwymyn space proposal; job order form for land surveyor; James H. Bell, Jr.; opinion and idea paper on rezoning areas inside Twin Oaks called "Rezone in the ozone;" varnish facility vote.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1982-1983, 11 items. (Box-folder 35:9)
      Meeting notes on Ridge Road, space for indexing, solar kilns and grain bins; recommendation on cow loafing shed; CLW shelter, construction of cow loafing shed, building site study priority; two spiral notebooks of meeting notes (includes two notebooks)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Kitchen Dining Complex, 1983-1984, 25 items. (Box-folder 35:10)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Kitchen Dining Complex, 1983, 25 items. (Box-folder 36:1)
      Opinion and idea papers about moving Llano road; meeting notes on land use and space use policy, move Fairs Trailer, placement of phone lines, moving the burn pile and bike shed, and recommendation for the doghouse; notebook of meeting notes.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Kitchen Dining Complex, 1983-1985, 23 items. (Box-folder 36:2)
      Opinion and idea papers about moving Llano road; meeting notes on land use and space use policy, move Fairs Trailer, placement of phone lines, moving the burn pile and bike shed, and recommendation for the doghouse; notebook of meeting notes. OS Area map.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1984, 9 items. (Box-folder 36:3)
      Meeting notes and opinion and idea papers.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1985, 6 items. (Box-folder 36:4)
      Meeting notes. Meeting notes approving proposal for patio type deck and storage of chimney brushes in the Bozo Shed; PUD questionnaire; Manager proposal; opinion and idea paper on how land planning functions.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Courtyard Shuffle, 1984-1986, 10 items. (Box-folder 36:5)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Courtyard Shuffle. Meeting notes, 1985-1986, 24 items. (Box-folder 36:6)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1986, 17 items. (Box-folder 36:7)
      Meeting notes and opinion and idea papers; committees will be appointed for the dairy barn site, Courtyard Shuffle, compost location, recreational playfields, relocate video; moving mailboxes to Zhankoye; opinion and idea papers on space use issues, future residences, layout of the buildings and other space and land use ideas, storage solutions, site of the pig pen, piano for Zhankoye basement, beer making and other activities in Zhankoye; planners recommendations.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Llano Remodel, 1986, 20 items. (Box-folder 36:8)
      Meeting notes and opinion and idea papers on Llano remodeling; meeting notes on design team and office plans; correspondence about planning process.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Oneida Bath, 1985-1986, 4 items. (Box-folder 36:9)
      Budget; plans; survey results; priority request.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Playfield, 1986, 3 items. (Box-folder 36:10)
      Meeting notes on basketball court and soccer field; proposals.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Pool or Pond, 1986-1989, 18 items. (Box-folder 36:11)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Pool or Pond, 1990-1991, 16 items. (Box-folder 36:12)
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Visitor Center, 1985- 1986, 14 items. (Box-folder 37:1)
      Progress papers on the visitor center; meeting notes; Visitor Cottage Weekly Review.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1987; 1989, 25 items. (Box-folder 37:2)
      Meeting notes and opinion and idea papers; list of general recommendations for storage, and smokers space; meeting notes on storage space and usage for the former Dairy Barn, Zhankoye Playground Siting; 'Old' Dairy Barn Survey for possible uses; remodel outline for new products office; possible uses for the former Chimney Shop; planners recommendations for the former Chimney Shop; storage shed proposal; request to move playing records; request for more space for the Child-Adult residence; land planning policy and manager proposal; building project surveys; request for a new software office; new painting for tool wagon and chair trailer. OS Member comments/opinions.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. What to Build Next, 1987, 18 items. (Box-folder 37:3)
      Opinion and idea papers on the process of planning a residence, Nashoba; meeting notes from the Planner's Forum on a new residence.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 37:4)
      Opinion and idea papers about removal of old green house and freezer shed, remodeling of the hammocks shop, making a hammock garden; meeting notes on the rope machine area upgrade.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning, 1989, 6 items. (Box-folder 37:5)
      Opinion and idea paper about long term building planning; opinion and idea paper requesting space for nudity behind Llano; opinion and idea paper about the space at Tupelo; opinion and idea paper in favor of a smaller residence building; opinion and idea paper supporting a lounge in Zhankoye; request to remove license plates from the Fairs Shed.
    - Planning Council. Land Planning. Room Crunch Member Surveys, 1991, 64 items. (Box-folder 37:6)
      Room Crunch Member Surveys; request for a tree house.
    - Planning Council. Legal, 1978-1986, 21 items. (Box-folder 37:7)
      Product Liability Insurance for hammocks; bylaws and Articles of Incorporation; proposal to change by-laws to allow longer terms for planners; separation agreement for a husband and wife who are members; child membership proposal as a means to reduce taxes; annual corporate registration with the State Corporation Commission.
    - Planning Council. Legal, 1987-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 37:8)
      Revision of by-laws; meeting notes.
    - Planning Council. Legal issues of members, 1980; 1986, 14 items. (Box-folder 37:9)
      A member of Twin Oaks is accused of stealing jewelry from a Charlottesville Jeweler, George Moody; a member has stolen money from Twin Oaks and there is discussion about how to obtain repayment from the member and whether or not to press charges; a legal contract for a member of Twin Oaks who owes Twin Oaks for medical school loans.
    - Planning Council. Legal. Tax bill, 1981-1987, 10 items. (Box-folder 37:10)
      Twin Oaks tax policies.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Acceptance process, 1981-1992, 26 items. (Box-folder 37:11)
      Discussion and feedback regarding new or returning membership applicants.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Gender Balance, 1979, 1 item. (Box-folder 37:12)
      Meeting to consider ways of recruiting more women.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Guests, 1975-1987; n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 37:13)
      Opinion and idea papers informing other members about specific guests; letters from guests requesting to stay longer; reminders of policies for having guests.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Member issues, 1987-1989, 10 items. (Box-folder 38:1)
    - Planning Council. Membership. New Members information, 1983-1985, 7 items. (Box-folder 38:2)
      Behavioral guidelines; information on holidays; copy of membership agreement; map of Twin Oaks.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Policies, 1981-1987, 16 items. (Box-folder 38:3)
      Membership and guest policies; opinion and idea paper on waiting period for new members; membership application; legal appeal system after rejection; policy for re-accepting ex-members.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Poll for Ideas, 1976-1984, 4 items. (Box-folder 38:4)
      Membership survey; opinion and idea papers; notes about feedback from children on new members.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Status. Associate, 1984-1986, 8 items. (Box-folder 38:5)
      Opinion and idea paper on associate status; paper from a member requesting associate status; discussion of policies on associate status.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Status. Dual Membership, 1976-1981, 4 items. (Box-folder 38:6)
      Policies; dual membership agreement form; papers on dual membership.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Status. Residency, 1978-1985, 8 items. (Box-folder 38:7)
      Opinion and idea papers about members on residency status; policies on residency status.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Transition, 1972-1987, 15 items. (Box-folder 38:8)
      Opinion and idea papers about members leaving; proposals for facilitating the leaving process; information about loans for leaving; opinion and idea papers about car privileges and ownership.
    - Planning Council. Membership. Turnover & Retention, 1975-1985, 6 items. (Box-folder 38:9)
      Opinion and idea papers and proposals on turn over and rewarding long term members. OS Bulletin about Exodus, a meeting wherein members discuss the departure of many prominent Twin Oaks members.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Analysis, 1979-1980; n.d., 21 items. (Box-folder 38:10)
      Proposal analysis; surveys forms used in the planning process.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning: Appendix B, n.d., 9 items. (Box-folder 38:11)
      Goals and value evaluation sheets.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Community Planners, 1981, 6 items. (Box-folder 38:12)
      Resource guide to help members live by the goals that were articulated in the planning process.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. East Wind, 1979, 17 items. (Box-folder 39:1)
      Three year plans for social interaction, new member orientation and integration, equality of the genders, sex ratio, cleanliness and house, skills, domestic agriculture, regionalism objectives and goals; Evaluation phase; Newsletter on Communication from the Federation of Egalitarian Communities; Comprehensive Planning Project; objectives survey; Values survey.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Excerpts for Evaluation, 1979; n.d., 29 items. (Box-folder 39:2)
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Fantasy Day, 1979, 91 items. (Folder 39:3)
      Members describe ways in which they would like to see Twin Oaks reflect their goals and values; notes on fantasies about dining, health and safety, population, housing and many aspects of their living at Twin Oaks; list of goals and values and negative relationships; ideas about the labor credit system; guidelines for accepting children.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goals and Values, 1971; 1975-1977; n.d., 55 items. (Box-folder 39:4)
      Minutes of the DAS group; information about a workshop; meetings about low morale; copy of a membership agreement; opinion and idea paper about the Tupelo living situation; meeting notes about concerns relating to personal spending, social behaviors that create anger, the hammock shop budget, and reevaluating Juniper's branch government; linkage groups. OS List of goals.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goals and Values, 1978-1979, 50 items. (Box-folder 39:5)
      Proposal by a study committee for small groups living together; meeting notes from five individuals who develop a social planning proposal for small group living using a matrix system or survey from members about their goals and values; notes on goal grouping (oversize).
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goals and Values, 1980-1981, 37 items. (Box-folder 39:6)
      Social planning materials packet; opinion and idea papers about small group living; proposals for small living space; interviews on space use at New Tupelo. OS Matrices.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goals and Values. Activities, 1979, 64 items. (Box-folder 39:7)
      List of general activities; proposals for small group spaces; priorities shopping list; notes on values list; interview on space use at new tupelo; small group surveys; opinion and idea papers on values; information on linkage groupings; diagrams; meeting minutes; goals; non-credit activities; goal groupings.